all right
markdown
blocks what are markdown
blocks uh We've started talking about
markdown and we talked about markdown
headings uh as the very first thing but
the truth is is that a heading is just
one type of markdown
block um a markdown document is
separated into multiple blocks and in
order to understand markdown this is
very very important in fact it's
impossible to
parse uh modern markdown without two
passes through the document the first
pass breaks up all of the document into
blocks and the second pass takes those
blocks and operates on each block almost
as if it was its own document its own
entity so to speak so there has to be
two passes and this is because of some
of the convention
that have made it very easy to um
organize readable content which was the
goal of markdown created by writers and
not scientists but it makes it extremely
hard to par um if if you don't
understand this but understanding this
idea of blocks um is super important as
you're writing it um and at least one of
you is going to say you mean bullets and
paragraphs I yes that's what I mean so
let's get into it here are all of the
block types in markdown so we're going
to go back to our get a uh repo you
should already have one of these and you
see already it says sample here right uh
I'm actually going to rename this one uh
this is actually about headings and I'm
going to go to the code and I want to
change this one about headings that we
did in another video I'm going to call
it headings okay so uh let's actually
call it notes uh we can say uh markdown
or MD headings right so MD is the
standard extension for that um that's
pretty much the one you should use you
there's many that are supported but
that's the one I suggest um and we're
going to commit that change and that's
going to rename MD headings to there so
let's make a new document here um add
file we're going to add this time we're
going to we're going to add MD and we
could we could put this in their own
subdirectory all kinds of things but
let's call it MD blocks okay MD uh in
this case you do want suffixes I did a
video about stop naming your scripts
with suffixes this is not the same thing
right this is you definitely want
suffixes here so we're going to go ahead
and commit that we're going to make a
new file and we're going to go edit this
file uh with our editor uh there's
actually multiple ways of editing um
giab desktop is actually pretty damn
cool giab Deb is really cool as well uh
I'll let you play with that we're just
going to use a plain old text editor and
we're going to do all of the different
types of blocks okay we're going to
actually have a sample of each um uh
heading uh is a block um okay um so a
heading itself is a block now strictly
speaking um you can have another one
right away but don't do that okay don't
do that blocks this is I'm going to I'm
going to say something here that's going
to be controversial but it always works
better if you have a blank line between
your blocks and I guarantee you you will
see people that do not do this um and
you know that's fine it the the the the
specification the
non-specific um does not require that
there necessarily be a blank line but
there is more than one
substantial uh application including
pandoc that for Pand flavor markdown
requires there to be a blank line
separating the blocks it makes it much
more readable in my opinion and it'll
just save you some headaches so even
though uh you could technically have
this separating your blocks um and you
know the beginning you see how that's
two blocks this is technically two
blocks even though one's on one and
one's on another it's just easier to
have that blank line um it's about a dis
point that I should say that blank lines
or lines that just have spaces in them
uh White space depending on how the
parser interprets that usually that
includes tabs but not always um is a
matter of of taste if I mean there's
nothing wrong with that it will end up
putting it as two blocks okay so that is
the first the first block the first type
of block is a
heading um the most important type of
block is a paragraph This is a
paragraph uh uh that that can have
multiple uh lines in it and this is
going to be very controversial
uh okay so uh and it can also have
formatting um so you'll see in the
preview that it makes
paragraph um something right away you'll
know uh still the same
paragraph right so you'll see this and
it's the same you see how I put it on
the same when I wrapped it uh markdown
strictly speaking uh does not see line
returns as
as a separation you remember that thing
I said I'm sorry you guys can't see
remember that thing I I told you I told
you about like the having a blank line
well for a paragraph you have to have a
blank line so if you have to have a a
blank line to end a paragraph block
might as well put a blank line after
everything it just makes it easier it's
more consistent um I'm I'm sorry sorry
leanda yeah so this is a paragraph as
you can see there's another one uh this
uh uh same so all of these when you
click on preview here you'll see they
are still all wrapped together into a
single paragraph now the the cont did I
not show it again I did it again didn't
I I'm so sorry I'm such a bad streamer
bad streamer uh this is a paragraph We
have multiple lines in it's still the
same paragraph same these things are all
showing up as one paragraph right
non-wrapped paragraph now this is
extremely controversial right um and I
don't know how to get into this other
than to show you um what I I let me I
don't know if I even want to get I tell
you what I'll do another video about it
okay I'm going to do another video about
this um let me make sure I put it in my
thing um extra uh I'm going to put an
extra in here extra should I uh wrap my
paragraphs
um blocks or not this is a hugely
controversial topic uh and there are
some very definite uh advantages and
disadvantages you don't need that as a
beginner you don't need to understand
that um you just need to know that
anything here that has a line return is
automatically in the same paragraph but
you know you could have just done this
and this is kind of making my
point uh here here is a bunch of other
stuff and you know that'll still be the
same paragraph right and it
automatically wrapped because I'm
putting it in here right well you know
what what if I had a line like this and
then I had another line another line
like this you know you see you see how
this can kind of this kind of gets at
the the problem this is still a single
paragraph you know what I mean because
the line returns are
ignored uh ugly
uh really uh ugly and you get kind of
get like well is this a paragraph or not
right is just pick
one you know what I mean just pick one
um I personally am more a fan of just
using I don't I don't put any line
returns in there and one of the reasons
is because of something that you need to
know about paragraphs the paragraph
block um we're not going to get into all
the cool things you can do to the text
inside the paragraph block that will
come in another video called inline
formatting so look for that video if you
want to know how to do bold and all that
okay um that's called yeah inline
formatting but somebody has already
guessed what I'm about to say if if you
get into the habit of doing this if you
get into the habit of wrapping your own
things like this you can very easily
make a mistake and put two spaces at the
end and if you have a space at the end
even though you can't see it you now
have a problem
because it will make uh it's it's not
doing it oh my God this is exactly what
I'm talking
about okay you see that still the same
paragraph what did it do
there you see what it
did it used one of the things that one
of the most controversial horrible
things we'll we'll talk about it when we
do formatting again when you put two
spaces at the before a line return it's
the same as inserting a line break
and so you know do you want a line break
maybe you do maybe you don't maybe you
just forgot and you put Extra Spaces at
the end and now you have new lines and
you're like why does my paragraph look
so weird all right this is the reason
that I do not use it took me a long time
I used to be a big big rapper kind of
guy um and now I'm not now I make if
it's a paragraph It's one big long line
it's one big long line effectively and
and that just saves me from the hassle
of dealing with line returns that might
sneak in and then I get what I want the
same thing I want all the time um there
are a couple obvious cases of using
double spaces um to do things um one of
the things might be like like like um
like um uh roses are red space space
enter violets are blue but there's
actually better ways to do this um in my
opinion so you know there might be times
when you want to force those line breaks
uh in the middle of your
block and there are tons of MD lenters
that prevent this in fact uh Jay has
been talking to us about they're making
their own tool it's funny they mentioned
that ATX headings are not even supported
in their tool um so a lot of people
don't like the double line thing so it's
worth mentioning to you so now you know
okay um
normally I would cover that whole line
return thing as a part of inline
formatting because technically it's an
inline format token but you get the
point right so the second type of block
is a paragraph the first type is a
heading um the third type of block
there's it's actually kind of there's
like kind of two types to it both of
these are called lists so I'm going to
call the third type is a list and
there's a subtype of list uh the first
type of list that you know is what's
called an order an unordered lists so
here's here's um uh a thing uh another
thing I don't know if you noticed but
when I hit enter it detects that I have
a list uh yet another thing this is
called a bulleted list uh it's actually
called specifically it's called an
ordered list because the way it's
rendered completely depends on the
renderer do not I'm going to say this do
not count on bullets and on on circles
being there there is no rule that that
says an ordered list has to have
bullets it can have any number of things
in fact um when you use one um is a real
time preview or typing as you're typing
a markdown there are ways to do that
using different types of editors there
are um the when you use vs code one of
the best reasons to use vs code is you
can see real- time uh sorts of things
like that uh and it'll show you I use
terminal based stuff and it actually
kind of sort of shows me um vs code uh
any type of markdown uh automatically
displays with a previewer right next to
it and um we haven't gotten to that
point yet we will get into editors when
we talk about writing code um and that
includes a look at vs code uh the number
one graphic based editor as well as Bim
and Neil Bim and all the things that
people like on the command line so but
but for right now as you can see I was
kind of going back and forth so preview
um here you go you can see that this is
a bullet okay now it goes without saying
that there's going to be another type of
block here um and somebody's going to
ask can I do su list items the answer is
yes but we're not going to quite do that
yet we'll get to that in just a second
uh there's also stack edit there's
there's a number there's a number
actually you have the URL for that uh CD
uh there there are a number of sites
where you can do markdown if you that
will do uh better than GitHub but I
didn't want to overwhelm people
um yeah so I think there is what's there
is um in browser markdown yeah oh gosh
my eyes my eyes are now gone I have lost
my my
eyes extended markdown support this is
cool um start writing yes please please
make it dark mode I want dark mode
where's my dark
mode is please next skip um where's dark
mode so stack at .io this is one of many
of them there are a bunch of them um and
and by the way if you don't want to
watch my video you can just go through
here the reason I'm doing I'm doing a
video at all is I want you to see that
there are some things that I don't think
you should do and so I'm going to have a
chance to talk about about there's kex
which is math Jax um which we'll get to
so anyway you can play with that for
then uh let's go back to our our
GitHub um don't use the
previews uh uh you can with your writing
having something not look like you want
it to be
yeah uh some people use obsidian I hate
obsidian reasons I'll talk to you later
about that um so anyway let's the next
block type is
bullets um and I do think we should have
videos about all the different editors
out there and I appreciate you guys
recommendations so but right now we're
just using good old GitHub to show you
what things look like on GitHub uh this
is called an order list so one to now
this is actually one of the times when I
really don't like um I I really don't
like what GitHub has chosen to do here
some of these editors think they're
helping you by changing the syntax of
markdown and doing the auto numbering
but here's the problem with this some of
these things are smart enough to reorder
it right so like if I copy this and I do
enter here and I paste it it's going to
do the re it's going to reorder it or
whatever right but I'm not a fan of this
and the reason I'm not a fan of this is
because if you stick I'm just I'm
warning you right now you can make your
own decisions But I'm warning you right
now if you stick with the ones you will
be happier and the reason you'll be
happier is let me give you an example so
look at what I'm doing in here um can I
read what the numbers are right now no I
can't but what if what happens when I
want to reorder something oh I want to
put this one up here
right by by using the one dot and
keeping at the one dot and not using the
auto numbering you're not forcing
everybody after you to use the same
auton number formatting if you don't use
the one if you use an auto Auto number
like we just did first of all there's
nothing that says it even has to be a
number period right it just says ordered
what if somebody wants to use the letter
A or or or you know any number of other
things and if you go if you what I'm
talking about go look at my skill. when
you look at these rendered things right
so when you look at the rendered one on
Ser you say learn markdown ABCD right so
so the whole point of markdown not
ordered list is making a very unique
very
centralized uh very common way to do
ordered numbering and then let the
renderer do the numbering don't do the
numbering in in the thing and so this is
one of the biggest gripes I have with
these kinds of tools is a lot of them
will try to do the numbering for you uh
and a lot of them uh said let's let's
yeah um yeah uh yes we're not going to
fight about editors right now please um
yeah
uh yeah this is right the whole build
yes okay um so anyway markdown is the
thing um and this is the way we're going
to use it um and
I dare you I I I like editors are a very
personal choice and I have my my choices
we're not going to fight about those
right now um can you turn off auto
number you know what I don't know uh I
imagine we probably can I'm not I've
never tried it actually um it does use
spaces no WP oh look at that line mode
no WP um I don't know maybe there is
there probably is if you find it let me
know uh obviously I don't use this for
my markdown but um but you might if you
do find that please let us know
um so anyway let let's get through the
rest of the block types we got quite a
few to go not not a lot but um so before
we leave um I mean God look at that do
you see how confused it is that's not a
new block type this is this is this is
broken my opinion anyway so so we have
what's called an ordered list and an and
an I'm sorry an ordered list here and an
unordered list the reason those words
I'm using those words very specifically
the term ordered and unordered come from
the HTML specification the reason they
didn't say bulleted and numbered is
because there's no guarantee that they
be bulleted and numbered and I want you
to know that when you get into this okay
the terminology is ordered and unordered
so so we have an ordered list here
whoops here and an unordered list here
the unordered list can be rendered
however you want to in your renderer by
default with numbers but the but the
token that's being looked for is a one
dot uh followed by an optional Space by
the way it's probably worth mentioning
that in your bulleted lists th that
space is not always required but is a
really good idea uh in fact I would
suggest that you should always put a
space after your tokens in this case a
one dot uh and then a single space is a
token um it just makes your stuff easier
to read um and and it will go down it is
a super set HTML yes uh I think it's
fair to stick with HTML naming yes uh
you can also use a BNC for your ordered
list but I would not do that um again
again everybody's going to have
different opinions on this my my
suggestions are based on the least
amount of things to remember the least
amount of pneumonic overhead I I do not
want to have to think about how to do a
bulleted list not only that but the
methods that I'm telling you these list
items these work in medium they work in
slack they work in lots of things where
other things are not supported so a lot
of things wonderful things people are
Sugg gesting I happen to know for a fact
are not supported by other markdown is
kinds of things such as slack and so
these recommendations are being based on
what I've personally experienced to be
the most common out there um and that
that's why I call it basic markdown it's
less to remember it works in the most
number of places and you know you're
less likely to be surprised by a tool
it's one of the reasons I don't like um
some of the tools like obsidian that
encourage diversion from things that are
that are usable across the board
everybody you know wants a common
standard where you can get that um some
people use dashes here I have people who
swear by dashes and I actually could be
convinced to use dashes
here um you know what I'm glad you
brought that up thank you pink rubber
boots
um uh just supported as a list in all
parsers
yeah I think I think star is supported
you know what I actually like that
better
I think as of this day I'm going to
change my buddy my buddy that I work
with squares by dashes as well for all
the same reasons that you just cited and
um one of the biggest reasons to do this
is because of this um this is is Watch
What
Happens you see that this turn it tries
to make it
bold actually if I put this on the other
side um it'll try to make it into a
thing oh sorry gosh sorry guys so watch
oh God I I am such a I'm going to use
dashes from now on thank you for saying
that this is why this is why we have a
community because we can help each other
out so one of my peers said that they
use Dash and that because it supported
all over and it was easier and it was
cleaner and it also plays well it plays
better with this which is uh a GitHub
ISM you see that so the bulleted items
become I could see so I see a strong
case for using Dash so much so I'm going
to change my my practice uh
from now on to start using dashes
another another reason to use dashes in
my opinion um yeah is bold and metallic
we're not going to do Bolden italic yet
um but that's actually one of the
reasons to do this uh let me show you
like if I'm if I'm here and I'm using uh
if I'm using a bulleted list I it's like
something
something uh other thing uh and dash
here right but if I'm using a this and
if I do it wrong you see that look what
just happened did you see how all my
formatting
changed did you see that now we haven't
done bold yet but that because there's
no space there and I'm trying to do a
bulleted item it thinks that all of this
stuff is bold so so to me that that
convinces me to use Dash because if I
screw up Dash it's still fine now it's
it's not a bulleted list because the
bulleted list item needs a space there
in pandoc anyway um but it doesn't blow
away everything else I I really like the
idea of Dash not to mention that you
know you can do the other thing like
this so I'm I'm a huge fan of the dash
um I have I have I have done the the
bullets because they look like bullets
for a long time um but I think that um
you can use any numbers from the top
level you can but don't I'm telling you
people don't do it because you're making
it so you can't cut and paste it into
something else right so one of the
reasons Okay so let's we're talk since
we're talking about lists let's get into
Su lists okay so now this is where
things get kind of weird because we
talked about the two types so this is
what's called an ordered list type so
let's do that uh here uh
comes uh comes an uh
ordered let's see unordered
list unordered list
um uh let's see and here is an ordered
list um you
know and I think Simplicity is key not
to mention compatibility so again with
markdown this is a constant issue
because there's so many different ways
to do markdown because it was never
standardized I mean there was a common
Mark standard which we'll get into but
um so here we go so we have we have a
list and an unorder list now I'm G to
I'm going to pause here if you're using
medium so if you medium.com which is
where a lot of people do blogging you
are not allowed to use nested list
items so before I get into nested list
items I want to encourage you to do one
thing I want to encourage you to try to
keep your lists at the top level almost
always when you're trying to do a n
nested list item you're starting to
depart from Clarity and you're you're
creating like a really huge table of
contents or something like that and
there are very valid reasons for doing
that one of those being uh what I'm
doing here right so what I'm doing here
is now the thing is going to blow your
mind is that this here this is another
list this is a list inside of another
list right and so I mean but this is
this is an outline so an outline is is
is a pretty clear usage of that but my
what I'm going to say again is if you
can maintain Simplicity particularly if
you're communicating in an article style
or blog try to stick with single top
level list and maybe present another
list uh at the top level with its own
introduction I'm just going to encourage
you to do that a lot of people don't do
that if you are planed to write on
medium you have to do that they've made
that a mandatory thing so so now now
that we have this you you know that you
can actually do uh a sublist now this is
where markdown the markdown convention
breaks down it breaks down big time and
this is going to be one of the first
times that we're going to look at the
common Mark
specification oh my Lord a sub bomb
thank you so much for the sub bomb holy
moly oh my goodness thank you so much
for the sub pom I have to take a moment
out of that is fantastic um I might have
to change views though because uh I
think the alerts are going to be going
off for a while um let me turn twitch
off for a second thank you so much for
the subs um that was really great thank
you thank you thank you all right so
back to where we are here so we're
looking at at at
markdown and we oh God what am I
doing all right so here here are the two
lists that we have and we're just
keeping it at the high level now you
might think okay I want to have a thing
uh I want I let's have a thing under a
thing uh so I'm going to going to type
one I'm going to type two letters in I'm
going to put a space I'm going to put a
sub thing uh a sub thing right now let's
actually preview this this is where
stuff gets really messed up okay now
that one saw that as a sub thing right
but if you do that in if you do that
inside of certain other um languages it
will not be the same and this is the
first time so I'm actually going to do a
search here common mark specification so
uh I was going to save this for a
separate video but we're going to go
ahead and and and jump in uh actually no
we're not I'll do this video separately
uh we do need to know um yeah we need to
do y common Mark extra y common Mark
I'll do that after that we do we do
these common Mark so sorry for the
Divergence there God damn that that that
that is going to kill my eyes my friends
I don't know what's going on there um
sorry for your your eyes I really
apologize uh I'll try
not so here we go so heading as a
block um so we got a sub thing here and
in the edit here we're going to get uh
we're going to try this here so we're
going to say uh let's like try to do
this so one two spaces and we can say
one dot you could say one uh one dot I
don't know do one one how about that uh
let's try that and say
preview and we get oh it didn't work Why
didn't it work right uh the reason it
didn't work is because there is no
standard here so whereas a bulleted list
and get a flavored markdown needs two
spaces to indicate a sub item uh when it
comes to an ordered list it doesn't see
it the same
way um
uh you can use Dash inside the order
list yeah but technically speaking when
you're doing that you're combining lists
so let's stick with the same type of
list and this is where things you start
to lose people oh my Lord oh my Lord
thank you for that level five H train
holy cow thank you so much for that okay
so so here we have another list item oh
my goodness this is crazy I guess we
have our wow that is like insane
we reached our goal and everything you
guys are the best I I am so
happy go back I'll I'll keep working
hard here I so appreciate it um my
friends that's fantastic um okay so so
here here we have another ordered list
and we can see that this one didn't now
this is this again this is where we
diverge from the standard because there
is no standard there at this point
there's no standard right so GitHub has
decided that if there's two spaces you
get a sub bullet right and when we're
over here if you have if you have two
spaces you don't get a sub bullet for a
numbered list now that's pretty damn
annoying and I want you all to see how
annoying that is because you know what
the hell right how do I do it
consistency well it turns out that the
people who made uh pandok and common
Mark decided Well we need to make it so
that it's consistent so if you had four
spaces is now you have consistency right
how would you possibly know that as a
beginner right so now we have one
I and it apparently now it sees it as a
sub thing now why did it pick one
instead why did it pick that number
instead of some other number you know is
that is that a you know it has nothing
to do with by the way with the number so
actually let's try three what does three
do three does the same thing so so it
turns out that get a play markdown needs
three or more I actually use four
consistently throughout because that's
what most use so if you're going to use
subbers I strongly encourage you to use
four um and here's a give here's another
example so if I'm using if I want to do
a sublist in pandoc which you also use a
markdown technology and I do one two and
I want to put uh something here it sees
it because it understands it until it
gets rendered and the reason it doesn't
work is because it uses a python
markdown renderer you see what I'm
saying it gets really confusing because
everybody does markdown slightly
differently so I want you to be aware of
all those differences so when you go
into it you you can take away the most
common usage and and that's we watch the
video about common Mark but when it
comes to nested lists these are very
very problematic and the only way that I
know of to have it be consistent is to
always use four spaces one two 3 four if
you use four spaces that is observed by
python markdown it's observed by pandoc
it's observed by Comm Mark and gfm and
the reason that the number of spaces for
nested list items is so problematic is
it was never specified in the original
markdown Pearl program so so that is one
reasons to have a specification um so as
you can see if you put four here you're
safe right and you get you get the sub
list item so so I think that's enough
for us to to leave blocks um uh to leave
the nested list that in blocks the the
other piece of this to know is as
somebody already mentioned um you can
Nest other blocks in here and strictly
speaking you can Nest any Block in here
it doesn't have these these list items
by o sorry these list items are very
confusing because strictly speaking you
have an entire markdown document
available underneath each nested list
item and believe me if you're writing a
parser it's pain in the butt so 1 2 3 4
I can
have uh bullet uh bullet one and I can
have bullet two and you can see that we
get our bullets underneath our other
list this is not just it that's not the
only thing you can do you can actually
have another blank line and you can put
a full-blown paragraph here um as long
as it's here this is a
paragraph you see how this gets really
crazy remember that I said at the
beginning remember that thing I said you
might want to avoid the use of these
before you again before you start
thinking that you can use this as a way
to create a numbered header document I I
got to strongly recommend that you don't
do that because you you just will run
into problems where stuff is not does
not consist what I want you to see here
is that this bullet this order uh
unordered bulleted list block uh and
another block this is paragraph these
two blocks appear inside of this two
block so this this this is a block and
then these are subblocks that are
contained within this outer block and
this is let's give you just a little bit
of preview of the HTML involved um for
this H it is a pain in the but look at
all the div stuff here doesn't even look
like HDML this is what they call div
soup um you see here there's a paragraph
here comes the ordered list uh they even
have a paragraph data damn they didn't
even they didn't even use HTML there it
is ordered list um and then there's the
list item see there's the list item
we're going to do all this HTML but what
would you rather learn markdown or HTML
after seeing that right um okay so so
the take away from this is is quite
simple um let's keep it simple let's
keep it simple let's try not use a bunch
of nested things um if you're going to
Nest you can uh but just be really
careful and seriously the main takeaway
is use four spaces for your sub list
items use four spaces okay four
spaces uh and there's a lot of them
there's there's npm there's there's a
ton of them um there's mpm for markdown
creation there's there the the reason
that we're talking about markdown
generically um in the most universal way
possible right now is because everybody
does it differently slightly and it's
it's hard it's hard to know what to do
that's going to work with everything the
only way to know that is to have
extensive experience with all of the
different tools that are out there and
that's something that I personally
obsessed with I've written my own
markdown parsers I written my own meta
languages that parse meta definitions of
other languages so that I can write my
own language parsers um and I got to
tell you this is one of the most
problematic places uh in the
documentation World um so there are a
lot of tools out there okay we got to
get through the rest of the blocks video
this has been a long one but I
appreciate everything that's happened
here um so what do we have so far we
have a heading block we have a paragraph
block uh that includes the that includes
the blank line by the way uh we have
another paragraph block and then we have
a we have a uh unordered list block and
each of these strictly speaking each of
these is also these I wasn't going to
say it before but I'm going to say it
now each of these is what's called a
list item block so this is a list item
this this here is both a list and a list
block and a list item block so this this
entire thing is a list block and the
list block is broken up into list item
blocks this is a list item block this is
a list item block and this is a list
item block and as you can see the sub
the list items can have inside
themselves they can have their own
blocks so down here we have that this
here is a list block um this here is you
know this is a list item right this is a
list block with one list item then we
have uh another list item that contains
uh its own list block with two list
items and so on um and it gets very very
very hairy um and so you know you just
need to make a decision about what
you're going to use what tools you're
going to use um but that is a block
okay so those are those the list blocks
as you can see are I think are some of
the most confusing there's also what
happens if there's spaces right what
happens if there's a space between two
blocks this is a very unpredictable
behavior um as you can see one two three
right now it did not start over right if
I do
this what is it going to do this
behavior is is defined differently
depending on the tool you're using in
GitHub it keeps it all in the same item
you put another thing here uh something
else you put another block type in there
and you preview that and that starts the
numbering over because it sees it as a
new block um these are something called
long lists in the specification and I
don't want to get into it it's a pain
it's a real pain so so maybe not use it
uh if you're going to have a list you
know kind of keep it clean um sometimes
if you have like a long paragraph maybe
you would want to do that and have a
numbered paragraph list um I guess that
would be something you might want to
consider but um go ahead and and take a
look at that let's get on with the rest
of the blocks though so we have a
heading block we have a paragraph block
uh we have an unordered items uh list
block we have an ordered list block and
um we have another couple very esoteric
block types uh but we're going to stick
with the most important ones um probably
one of the most important Tech blocks
that you'll ever see um is is this one
yeah partials and write your own tags
yeah that kind of stuff is out of scope
but yeah those are cool things there's
been a lot of stuff here so we're going
to use what's called a fence this is
called a code I call it a code fence um
I it's officially it's called a fence
and officially it has multiple uses so
in here we can write code right so if we
wanted to write a little bit of Shell
Code uh bsh Echo H
world and we could write a little bit of
Shell Code in there and this somebody
who's watching this video is going to
give me a bunch of stuff about this but
I want you to I want you to learn it the
simplified way and then and then I can
you can embellish and learn all the
other ways okay let's go ahead and
render this preview this um as you can
see it makes it this really pretty sh
it's not cool and you're saying to
yourself well wouldn't it be better if
it had syntax highlighting hold on to
your horses here we go so by putting the
name of the language you can pretty much
guess um you can you can just save that
and you it the markdown tool will
automatically render it for you so in
this case you see that it put it put
that in Gray and it's using a tool to do
the rendering um I do think it's
interesting that as soon as I made it
into shell you can click over here you
can cut and paste this and and all kinds
of really amazing things with this okay
these are the most important comp uh
components of you making notes right if
you're taking notes this is going to be
one of the most important ways to do
that uh here is a uh code fence and I'm
picking my language terms very
specifically here um because that's this
is It's called the fence post um
God it's so hard to do so we're gon and
preview that make sure it still works um
so some people call this a Verbatim or
whatever um this this is generally how
you will do code oh wow look at that I
lost my syntax oh no I'm looking at it
the wrong way okay so that is a code
fence right and that's all you need to
learn right now okay
um having having said that
you should know that you can put as many
dashes here of three and more you can
put like a a dozen of them right and but
why and I'm going to make a case for
using the simple the simplest possible
thing in the most consistent way three D
three back ticks is supported by slack
and
Discord five is not all right three is
you know it's become even though it
wasn't standardized that way that's
become the standard by using three you
can look through your code very quickly
and you can find all your code blocks
because you know exactly where they are
now the original designers of markdown
wanted you be have a lot of flexibility
there and one of the other ways to do
this and there's really only one use
case uh but what if I want to include
markdown in my code
pens okay there's really only one case
for this but you can also use these
tities right uh and then you can put
markdown
you can say this you can say uh
sh
right um so if I want this is a very
edge case but if I wanted to do this
right if I wanted to put my own example
into show you the markdown for my
example I need something else so in that
particular weird case you could use
these these triples uh you could use
tities or you could even use a fourth TI
if you want to show using tities you
know you can get kind of inception about
the whole thing you know keep going down
and down the whole the rabbit hole um
but as you can see the thing is so cool
about this is that this actually shows
you the markdown and it also synx
highlights the stuff inside of it which
I find particularly intelligent in terms
of parsing it's very very intelligent
parser to be able to pull that off
that's very hard um to do that but if
you want to
improve your chances oh by the way
there's the the symbol for mark down is
down in the corner there um so those are
called code blocks or code fences um
they're also sometimes called
verbatim uh sections and the reason for
that is because there's another form of
this that does not use the
fences and strictly speaking they are
the same things even though everybody
deals with them differently and um uh
but but what about
uh blocks uh that just start with spaces
okay so I have to show you this because
it's it's kind of mandatory but I never
use it I never ever use what I'm about
to show you um if I go one because the
number of spaces is different on every
single system if I do 1 2 3 4 I can do
this I can say this is some verbatim
uh code right and I could actually cut
and paste you know like an emoji or
something uh you know um hello you know
and by doing this this turn you see that
already changed it in the preview you'll
see it too here see that this is
verbatim code now you can't tell it what
syntax to use for this um so you know
like why would you do that um honestly I
don't know why the only way the only
reason I would ever use that would be if
I were going to maybe do cut and paste
some asky art or something but this is
literally the same thing as a code Pence
version my my take in this is don't do
it just don't it's not worth it it's not
worth it h because you have to maintain
the
indentation um you know I don't I don't
even know how to remove the I'm using my
mouse I don't normally use
Mouse so this is exact
um uh but why when this is the
same I think you should fence everything
I personally think you should use a
fence for everything because you can
find it there's literally no way to
search for in your document there's no
way to search for that verbatim text if
you use tabs only you can search for
everything that is indented for spaces
but but that would give you everything
in the bulleted list too so there's
really no reason to do that I think you
should do this personally uh not to
mention the fact that this is not
supported in slack or Reddit or anything
this is this these code fences that's
supported everywhere
Discord um so that's that that's that
kind of way of doing it thank you for
the follow um so so we're we're getting
very close to the end of all the
different block types uh the major block
types um so again there's
headings uh there are lists there's
paragraphs there's code fences um those
and then there's You Know Reba and
blocks those are the main types there's
one last one that's worth mentioning um
I you'll occasionally see this used uh
and this is a leftover for uh here is
something from an 80s
email uh with a bunch of lines
uh that um um I have to have arrow on
every
line okay so um
quotations quotations are
problematic and so let's look at them
this is really the last block type
besides reference blocks which is kind
of special and we'll talk about when we
do links but um you see how it puts the
thing here showing that that's a a
quotation now some people use this and
they really seriously abuse this uh it
makes it very hard to support so they'll
put because
because okay how do I say this a
quotation block is literally a separate
markdown document which means you can do
this um you can say I I want an
unordered list uh boo uh bar and and
when you preview it you can have that be
list because a quotation itself it the
block a quotation block is itself a full
markdown
document and that and when it comes of
paring is Annoying It's also the same
thing with list items but that's a
separate separate topic altogether um
that recursion becomes really
problematic what what's even more
problematic is how do you maintain it
like trying to edit this thing from the
command liner stuff is a pain in the
butt and so um uh I'm going to put a
thing here um Rob Rob
suggests Rob suggests uh uh just uh
using single line paragraph uh
quotations because if you only have a
single look at this this blank line
between Watch What Happens
so you see how it it is a separate
quotation right
but if I can't tell you how many times I
have been like trying to maintain a
quotation I'm like okay fine damn it I
wanted it to be part of the other one so
I have to put a little arrow there you
know what I mean um and so my take first
of all I don't use quotations very much
um you can use quotations all over you
can use them in in again in slack and
Discord and stuff like that um better uh
to just use uh uh quotation
uh for long
paragraphs and in my opinion in my
opinion it's better to just do it that
way you can do however you want um I I
try to uh go uh to toggle preview mode
Control Plus shift plus M that's a lot
of things control shift m control shift
M no it doesn't work for me not a my
keybard
anyway uh maybe I'm pushing the wrong
thing yeah no not for me control shift
plus M to toggle the Tab Key moves Focus
all right Escape then tab to move to the
next interactive I don't care um anyway
guys so yeah control shift M does not
work for me I'm so sad why doesn't it
work I do not
know it does not work this is one of the
reasons I don't like graphic editors
with Bim I know exactly what I'm going
to get every time I I never have to
second guess it um graphic editors are
like like
whatever yeah try Windows Windows shift
M yeah spend 20 minutes trying to figure
out how this one works
um yeah nothing nope uh command shift M
we're gonna end up losing all our code
let's go ahead and save our code before
we screw around with it
more because I don't want to break
it um yeah I I don't like I I have very
bad success with with graphic editor in
general I I just want to work I
mean stuff to work sorry for the wordss
I've been trying not to
um anyway so so there we go those are
the major block types so we have a
heading we have paragraph we have we
have ordered list unordered list um we
have code fences we have verbatim blocks
we have
quotations and um that those are the
main types um there is another type
called a reference list um and we will
we'll talk about that later when we talk
about links uh and inline stuff which is
going to get its own video um is there
any block type that I missed let's
actually ask Chad GPT what are what are
the markdown block types let's see what
chat GPT has to say uh headings
paragraphs block quotes code blocks
fence code blocks lists tables oh we
forgot tables we forgot horizontal lines
tables nested blocks links and images we
forgot links too I forgot some stuff I
did I forgot some stuff thank you Chad
jbt for reminding me um okay so we did
fence code blocks we did code blocks uh
we did lists we did not do tables we did
not horizontal line is so easy um okay
so the only thing you should know for
horizontal lines honest to God my
friends just just do the easy stuff I'm
not even kidding stick with four dashes
okay stick with four dashes um
um uh let's see a a it's actually not
even a horizontal line it's actually a
it's actually a semantic
separator um so it it was it it's in
pandoc it's not called the horizontal
line um it's usually rendered as a
horizontal line but it doesn't have to
be uh is is uh
for uh or uh
four dashes together so the reason that
I think you should just stick with this
is so you can find it you can search for
it um if you this is one of those things
that's like really crazy uh don't get
crazy with this with all the different
options there are crazy numbers of
options for this you can actually do um
you can do
stars um so you can do
stars uh you can inter miix Stars um and
the idea originally was to you know
create this really artistic asky art uh
in your in your markdown but that's
horrible if you're talking about making
a documentation database you don't want
that you want to be able to search
through and find everything and you
can't do that if you vary what you do as
your horizontal rule just use four
dashes my friends I'm telling you stick
with four dashes um and you'll be good
to go you'll be very happy um
technically that is a block so you know
thank you chat GPT for reminding us uh
what else did we forget tables um tables
is we did nested list by the way let's
see what ones we did Cover we cover Nest
BX we need to do links and images which
we can't really do links and images
until we do uh inline uh and so we'll do
links and images as a part of the inline
stuff um you can actually have Mar HTML
just don't use HTML I'm going to put
that in there right now uh never
include HTML in your markdown
it is not even allowed in most markdowns
including pandoc why because by by
including HTML and your markdown you
force every parser to handle to have
everything to support the entire HTML
syntax and GitHub tries to say well you
can use this subset of HTML things that
we consider safe you can never remember
what they are in fact the only HTML
thing that I would even consider using
in markdown is a mment uh and there's no
way to write comments and
markdown uh except maybe a comment so if
you wanted to turn off part of your
document um you could use an HTML
comment uh this uh HTML is this this um
this uh markdown
content uh which by the way this is not
a markdown thing that's that's actually
an stml comment uh which predates HTML
so uh is uh
disabled and will be
invisible when rendered okay so I would
say comment but even then why are you
why are you putting comments in your
documents right um especially since
you're you know just just don't do it so
there's no comments there um as I said
the um so just don't do the HTML you can
embed HTML basically guber said when
they made his Pearl script to do this
when guber made his Pearl script to
write all this stuff he he he did a
thing where it's like well well since
it's going to markdown was the
specification for the original markdown
says that markdown will only be rendered
as HTML and based on the original
creation of markdown that very Line in
the Sand bullet point of the original
design requires markdown to be rendered
as
HTML and markdown I'm going to tell you
right now markdown has grown well beyond
the confines of being rendered as HTML
people have written entire books in
markdown uh multimark there's many
different people write slideshows in
markdown people do you know chat in
markdown people they there's so many
different usages of markdown now that
like it or not whether ruber likes it or
not who's been very hands office with
his whole uh dealing with the old Mark
now think he was asked to be part of his
specifications team and just thumbed his
nose at the whole thing um which if you
compare it to jgm um you know the guy
who created B Pand has been searching
for striving for um standardization of
the whole thing um it's quite a contrast
anyway so so this is way more than about
markdown you ever wanted to know so by
by saying uh markdown automatically
includes all
HTML the comp the complexity of a of a
parser to handle and a renderer to
handle markdown goes through the roof
now you need to have basically an entire
web browser built into your renderer
whereas if you're just dealing with
markdown itself only you don't have that
so many many things have decided to turn
that off pandoc flavored markdown
forbids explicitly forbids any HTML get
a flavor markdown explicitly forbids
most HTML for the sake of security
concerns right um so so when you go out
on the internet and you read that snide
comment that says just put a an
HTML um you know class tag in there or
something and you'll be good to go
because my all markdown must support
HTML just know that that's like a really
really bad thing to do because you're
going to create documentation that's
going to go into your knowledge base
which is not going to be parsable and
usable by most things and most things
are going to see that as line noise and
they're not going to use it so um just
don't do it don't use HTML in your
markdown I should probably been its own
video Oh Well links and images we're
going to do in a separate video when we
talk about inline formatting technically
they are blocks but we're going to cover
that um and uh let's see nested blocks
we already talked about that the stuff
inside block quotes or list items uh
horizontal lines we did last thing we
need to do is tables and this is
actually an interesting one because
tables are not allowed in markdown this
was added to
markdown um they are not a part of the
original markdown I'm going to say that
again it's probably why I forgot it
tables are not a part of the original
markdown and they still have yet to be
specified they're not even a part of
common Mark the common Mark
specification does not define tables
however however there have been then
multiple extensions of markdown that
have allowed tables and uh that includes
G up flavor markdown so let's do tables
um so a table uh the simplest there's
many many types of tables that are
supported um the easiest it's not to me
it's not really the easiest these are
these are a pain they really are um but
if you want to do a table actually let
me let me write we'll just do one okay
so the top part let's start out with
this let's say like name uh and then a
bar uh and then we could say uh color
favorite favorite color all right and
then then you have a dash in between if
you want to you can make them spaced out
so they look nice and they look pretty
but I swear they have like tools that'll
help you maintain your tables um but
yeah and then you can say Rob uh I don't
know today my favorite color is blue uh
Doris uh she likes
um it's like T
turquoise it's I don't know I don't even
know the
name
turquaz um anyway my my control thing is
not working so I have to go through and
click on the
previewer
um so again oh wow it didn't work what
did I do
wrong what did I do
wrong I did something wrong do I have to
have the con I don't think I
do oh is it is it missing this
maybe uh I thought you could get away
with not using the
um I guess not I mean you don't oh no no
I know what it is you can't skip the
first one oh I'm sorry yeah because
that's the one that triggers it being a
table um yeah duh okay so you do need
that that needs that's that needs to be
there I
forgot
um yep yep yep yep all right so let's
try that that's these are the easiest
tables to write um they're not as pretty
they're not that pretty those are not
pretty
tables um those are really not pretty
tables when it comes to
um how you're going to you know m
maintain them now if if you want them to
be if you want it to be left Justified
you put this over here and then all this
stuff will be I'm sorry right Justified
if you put two it'll be centered by
default it's usually left
Justified and then and then you do your
preview God I I'm I'm hating going back
and forth like this maybe we should zoom
out can you guys can you guys still see
it okay so so there we go um you see how
the names are now right right Justified
um so that's it that's tables tables are
are really easy um to do I again I don't
normally keep them looking pretty
because I want to change the content and
I don't want to screw around with spaces
all the time uh but if you wanted to
make them look pretty you could um the
default is left Justified if you want to
center it then you do like this two of
these around two colons around it and
then it makes it
Center um they do have to match up and I
mean don't even go there there's other
ways to do this um and pandok has a
different way of doing tables as well
but this is what this is literally
called gfm tables they are a supported
format under Google and as I said they
are not a part of the common Mark
specification um in fact if you look for
the latest
version uh if you search for God this is
hurting my eyes so
badly I'm am so sorry uh footnotes
tables is there what convention put this
in other document
elements um there are no tables in here
period so so there so there that's a
that's that's why so um I think I think
that's it my friends this has been a
long video um to get through the
markdown thing uh but there we got all
the markdown blocks um and then probably
the last markdown video we will do uh
with regard to the syntax is going to be
inline elements inline elements and
images and we will do that next so once
you have this done yeah you can you know
you have something to save and click on
Commit changes and then you can go back
and and and read about it um using your
own document um I I don't have to tell
you that there are like literally
thousands of markdown tutorials out
there
online um always use chat GPT at table
does chat GPT use right do
tables it does
Chad GPT actually formats your tables in
markdown wow I did not know that I have
to try that so um so hopefully that has
been enough about blocks there's been a
lot in this video um and I mean it's
this video has been filled with with
opinions that are based on a lot of
experience using at least a dozen if not
more markdown renderers including
writing my own so I'm strongly going to
encourage you to consider these
simplifications before you go down the
rabbit hole of picking one flavor um
even the tables even the tables that you
use that you're already picking a flavor
um for the sake of the beginner boost we
are picking GI him flavored markdown as
our flavor um there are two more pie
major videos that need to be made uh
that go with this the one is the inline
formatting elements bold and italic and
all that how to link how to link to
things um the inclusion of IM
um which is probably going to be a
separate video and the use of things
like to include math for notation like
math Jacks and and and ktech and latch
and all that um and that's particularly
for scientific Computing and um those
kinds of things so those will be
separate videos look for those and um
stay tuned so go give us a try you can
start taking notes right now